John Dildine and Ginny Dildine papers
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
John Dildine and Ginny Dildine papers 1957-2014 1957-1995
AFC 2018/009
Dildine, John
Dildine, Ginny
1602 items; 12 containers; 88 linear inches.
3 sound cassettes: analog.
1225 items.
246 slides: color; 35 mm.
27 photographic prints: black and white; various sizes.
2 photographic prints: color; 3 1/2 x 5 in.
4 posters.
36 drawings.
59 artifacts.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The John Dildine and Ginny Dildine papers document their involvement in folk music, crafts, and other folk revival activities from the 1950s-1995. The Dildines played pivotal roles in the Folklore Society of Greater Washington, Fox Hollow Festival, and National Folk Festival Association. Their work with puppetry was important in the revival of that art form and the collection includes Ginny Dildine's sketches and patterns for puppets, photographs of puppet performances at festivals, and the Dildine Family manuscript songbook, with notations about puppet performances. Correspondents include Bob Beers, Evelyne Beers, Gordon Bok, George and Gerry Armstrong, Pete Seeger, Toshi Seeger, Mike Seeger, Michael Cooney, and others. The collection also includes fan mail for John Dildine's folk music radio programs. Photographs include color slides of the Fox Hollow Folk Festival (1966, 1970); Mariposa Folk Festival (1970, 1972); the Newport Folk Festival (1967) including photographs of Pete Seeger, Mike Seeger, Hedy West, Joan Baez, Buffy Sainte-Marie, and others; the Dildine puppets (1970s); the Folklore Society of Greater Washington picnic (1965), and the Smithsonian Folklife Festival (1967). The collection includes the transcript of an interview with John Dildine conducted by Julie McCullogh in 1993; and correspondence and outlines related to the Kennedy Center Honors video interview with Pete Seeger, conducted by John Dildine in Beacon, New York, June 7, 1995.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Beers, Bob, 1920-1972--Correspondence.; Beers, Evelyne--Correspondence.; Bok, Gordon--Correspondence.; Dildine, Ginny, collector.; Dildine, Ginny--Correspondence.; Dildine, John, collector.; Dildine, John--Correspondence.; Dildine, John--Interviews.; Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014.
Organizations
Folklore Society of Greater Washington.; Fox Hollow Folk Festival.; Mariposa Folk Festival.; Newport Folk Festival.
Subjects
Folk festivals--Canada.; Folk festivals--United States.; Folk music radio programs.; Folk music--Societies, etc.; Folk musicians--United States.; Folk songs, English--Texts.; Puppets.
Form/Genre
Clippings.; Correspondence.; Drawings.; Fan mail.; Photographs.; Posters.; Programs.; Songbooks.; Sound recordings.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: 1: Correspondence; 2: Professional activities; 3: Programs; 4: Sound recordings; 5: Photographic materials; 6: Drawings; 7: Posters; 8: Artifacts.
Acquisition
John Dildine; 2018.
Related Material
John and Ginny Dildine collection (AFC 1975/001), Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
John Dildine collection (AFC 1975/024), Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Access may be restricted. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Biographical Note
John Dildine and Ginny Dildine became familiar figures on the folk music scene in the 1960s, performing at various festivals, schools, and other venues. Around 1965 they began to incorporate puppetry into their stage performances. The puppets were designed by Ginny and either hand-operated or worn as costumes. Over the years the Dildine children (Scott, Debbie, and Connie) joined their parents onstage for musical performances, and to help operate the puppets. Among John’s many accomplishments, he was also the host of folk music programs on Washington, D.C.-area radio stations WASH and WAMU-FM (from 1957-1970) and was the first president of the Folklore Society of Greater Washington (1964-1965).
Scope and Content
The John Dildine and Ginny Dildine papers document their involvement in folk music, crafts, and other folk revival activities from the 1950s-1995. The Dildines played pivotal roles in the Folklore Society of Greater Washington, Fox Hollow Festival, and National Folk Festival Association. Their work with puppetry was important in the revival of that art form and the collection includes Ginny Dildine's sketches and patterns for puppets, photographs of puppet performances at festivals, and the Dildine Family manuscript songbook, with notations about puppet performances. Correspondents include Bob Beers, Evelyne Beers, Gordon Bok, George and Gerry Armstrong, Pete Seeger, Toshi Seeger, Mike Seeger, Michael Cooney, and others. The collection also includes fan mail for John Dildine's folk music radio programs. Photographs include color slides of the Fox Hollow Folk Festival (1966, 1970); Mariposa Folk Festival (1970, 1972); the Newport Folk Festival (1967) including photographs of Pete Seeger, Mike Seeger, Hedy West, Joan Baez, Buffy Sainte-Marie, and others; the Dildine puppets (1970s); the Folklore Society of Greater Washington picnic (1965), and the Smithsonian Folklife Festival (1967). The collection includes the transcript of an interview with John Dildine conducted by Julie McCullogh in 1993; and correspondence and outlines related to the Kennedy Center Honors video interview with Pete Seeger, conducted by John Dildine in Beacon, New York, June 7, 1995.
Container List
- Series 1: Correspondence
  Personal and professional correspondence, plus related materials, remain in their original order within each folder, except for delicate or multipage materials, which have been rehoused and placed and the back of their folder of origin.
  - Correspondence--folk music radio program (1 of 3), circa 1958-1994 (Box-folder 1/1)
    Contents of box-folders 1/1, 1/2, and 1/3 are from a single binder with this title. Box-Folder 1/1 includes the loose materials from the front pocket of the binder. Includes correspondence, newspaper clippings, publicity flyers and brochures, and related materials.
  - Correspondence--folk music radio program (2 of 3), circa 1958-1994 (Box-folder 1/2)
    See the description for box-folder 1/1. The folder includes a photo of Paul Clayton (AFC 2018/009: PH263).
  - Correspondence--folk music radio program (2 of 3), circa 1958-1994 (Box-folder 1/3)
    See the description for box-folder 1/1.
  - Correspondence regarding puppets (1 of 2), circa 1967-1995 (Box-folder 1/4)
    Includes typed and handwritten correspondence, plus schedules for events, flyers, newspaper clippings (originals and photocopies), and related materials for performances at various festivals and venues. Includes Ginny Dildine's membership card for The Puppeteers of America (1975).
  - Correspondence regarding puppets (2 of 2), circa 1967-1995 (Box-folder 1/5)
    See the description for folder 1 of 2.
  - Correspondence (1 of 2), 1952; circa 1972-2002 (Box-folder 1/6)
    Includes typed and handwritten correspondence, newspaper clippings, a contractual agreement with Gentle Wind, a photocopied article on the Symondsbury mumming play (1952), an original copy of The Purple Pumpkin, by Gerry and George Armstrong (and inscribed by one of them, for both), and related materials. Correspondence in box-folders 1/6 and 1/7 were received as a single group.
  - Correspondence (2 of 2), circa 1972-2002 (Box-folder 1/7)
    In addition to correspondence and related materials, the folder includes a ditto copy of Sampler of Christopher Robin Songs, with musical settings by Des and Juliet Rainey, and a ditto copy of The Mountain Dulcimer: How to Make It and Play It (After a Fashion), by Howard Mitchell. See description for box-folder 1/6.
  - Folklore Society of Greater Washington--folk music radio (1 of 3), circa 1957-2014 (Box-folder 2/1)
    Received as a binder with correspondence three-hole punched to fit. Received in reverse chronological order, an organization which has been retained (except for multi-page items, rehoused in bond paper folders). Typed and handwritten correspondence, from individuals and organizations. Also includes documentation related to FSGW's FiftyFest! (their fiftieth anniversary event), in 2014. John Dildine was the organization's first president. His ID badge for FSGW's FiftyFest! has been relocated to Series 8.
  - Folklore Society of Greater Washington--folk music radio (2 of 3), circa 1957-2014 (Box-folder 2/2)
    See the description for box-folder 2/1.
  - Folklore Society of Greater Washington--folk music radio (3 of 3), circa 1957-2014 (Box-folder 2/3)
- Series 2: Professional activities
  Documentation for the planning stages of puppet and music performances.
  - The Dildine Family: Folksongs with Visuals (1 of 5): front matter, circa 1970s (Box-folder 2/4)
    Materials in box-folders 2/4 through 2/8 were received in a single binder. They have been removed from the binder but maintained in their original order. The front matter includes blank sheets of paper and envelopes with the Dildine family logo and address, two ditto copies of the Dildine family's folk music and performance background and achievements, a copy of the liner notes/booklet accompanying the recording "The Dildine Family" (1974), and a sheet of handwritten notes.
  - The Dildine Family: Folksongs with Visuals (2 of 5): Section 1--organization, circa 1970s (Box-folder 2/5)
    See note for box-folder 2/4. This folder includes a two-page inventory of puppets, props, and gear, as well as where the materials are stored.
  - The Dildine Family: Folksongs with Visuals (3 of 5): Section 2--visuals, circa 1970s (Box-folder 2/6)
    See note for box-folder 2/4. This folder includes songs already used in the Dildine family's repertoire, represented by typed handwritten and photocopied lyrics, hand-drawn illustrations, and some music. Six small photos are taped, three to a page, to illustrate the lyrics for "Good Old Colony Days" and "Leatherwing Bat."
  - The Dildine Family: Folksongs with Visuals (4 of 5): Section 3--possible visuals, circa 1970s (Box-folder 2/7)
    See note for box-folder 2/4. This folder includes typed lyrics (with some handwritten notes) for songs that will be provided with visual elements at a future date.
  - The Dildine Family: Folksongs with Visuals (5 of 5): Section 4--no visuals, circa 1970s (Box-folder 2/8)
    See note for box-folder 2/4. This folder includes typed, handwritten, original, photocopied, and dittoed lyrics with some illustrations for songs that were not performed with visual elements.
  - "Songs from folk friends that we didn't learn," circa 1970s (Box-folder 3/1)
    Folder title accompanied original materials. Handwritten, typed, dittoed, and photocopied song texts and music.
  - "The Dildine Family," 1974; undated (Box-folder 3/2)
    Correspondence (including permission requests), booklet layout and design mock-ups, copy drafts, song lists, and other materials related to the production of "The Dildine Family Record," released in 1974. Includes the booklet in its final, published form. A letter to the Dildines from Gordon Bok, including extensive illustrations and on onion skin paper, remains in this folder.
  - WAMU-FM, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 3/3)
    A program with the broadcast schedule for July 1967 that includes a photo of John Dildine plus a brief biography, and a certificate awarded to John Dildine by the station as part of American University, in recognition of distinguished services (dated May 17, 1968).
  - Interview with John and Ginny Dildine, by Julie McCullough, October 3-4, 1993; October 20, 1995 (Box-folder 3/4)
    Edited, typed copy of the transcript. Accompanied by a printed copy of McCullough's paper, "Folklore Society of Greater Washington: Voluntary Association as Utopia?" (prepared for the Society for Utopian Studies's 20th annual conference, October 20, 1995). The paper is accompanied by a handwritten sticky note from McCullough to John and Ginny Dildine.
  - New Lost City Ramblers, 2006-2007 (Box-folder 3/5)
    A printed email thread between Thomas Stern and John Dildine (2006), a printed email thread between Ray Allen and John Dildine (2007), and a copy of the Institute for American Studies newsletter (Spring 2006).
  - Pete Seeger: Kennedy Center Honors video interview, 1995 (Box-folder 3/6)
    The interview was conducted on June 7, 1995. Related materials from 1995 include correspondence, and typed and handwritten notes. Included are copies of the consent form, signed by John Dildine and Dinah Smith (Executive Producer, Kennedy Center). In addition, there is a faxed set of illustrated directions to Seeger's home in Beacon, New York.
  - Photocopies of published materials, 2010; undated (Box-folder 3/7)
    Two stapled photocopies: one is of the 2010 essay "In Pursuit of Authenticity: the New Lost City Ramblers and the Postwar Folk Music Revival" (Journal of the Society for American Music, vol. 4, no. 3, and a few pages photocopied from an unidentified book.
- Series 3: Programs
  Personal and professional correspondence, plus related materials. Items remain in their original order within each folder, except for delicate or multipage materials, which have been rehoused and placed and the back of their folder of origin.
  - Festival of American Folklife, 1968; 1971 (Box-folder 3/8)
    Festival programs. Handwritten notes, including John Cohen's name, on the cover of the 1971 program.
  - Mariposa Folk Festival, 1967; 1969 (Box-folder 3/9)
    Festival programs. Handwritten note from John Dildine, on the cover of the 1969 program.
  - Newport Folk Festival, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 3/10)
    Festival programs.
  - Old Songs Festival (1 of 3), 1997; 2001-2003; 2005 (Box-folder 3/11)
    Festival programs; two copies of the 2005 program. While there is not a program per se for the 2007 festival, there is a preliminary schedule, a main stage schedule, a promotional flyer, and a preliminary campsite plan; these are accompanied by a printed email from Michael Silk to John Dildine.
  - Old Songs Festival (2 of 3), 2006; 2008-2009 (Box-folder 4/1)
    See description for box-folder 3/11.
  - Old Songs Festival (3 of 3), 2010; 2013 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Philadelphia Folk Festival, 1964; 1967-1968; 1970, 1974 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - National Folk Festival, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 4/4)
    Held at Wolf Trap Farm Park, in Vienna, Virginia; the folder includes The Performer, vol. 1, book 9 (1971).
  - Programs from various festivals, 1966-1967; 1973-1974 (Box-folder 4/5)
    Includes the 35th Annual Festival of the Puppeteers of America (1970), the Cape Island Festival of Folk Music and Crafts (1973), June Day Folk Festival (1974), a schedule for Antagonise (1973), and a copy of Philharmonic Hall, Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts (1966-1967).
  - Gentle Wind catalog, 1990 (Box-folder 4/6)
    Catalog of commercial recordings available from A Gentle Wind. Red notations are made for the three cassettes received as part of the collection.
- Series 4: Sound recordings
  - Dildine Family. The Dildine family. Albany, N.Y.: A Gentle Wind, 1982., 1 sound cassette: analog; stereo (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR01)
    GW 1017
  - Dildine, John and Ginny, with Gordon Bok. The reluctant dragon. Albany, N.Y.: A Gentle Wind, 1988., 1 sound cassette: analog; stereo (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR02)
    GW 1047
  - Dildine, John, and Marina Cross. A trunk full of tales. Albany, N.Y.: A Gentle Wind, 1982., 1 sound cassette (circa 45 min.): analog, 1 7/8 ips; stereo (Item-id AFC 2003/051: SR03)
    GW 1016.
- Series 5: Photographic materials
  - Folklore Society of Greater Washington Pick-nic, July 3, 1965, 28 slides: color; 35mm; AFC 2018/009: PH001-PH028 (Box 5)
    Photos from the first annual Pick-nic [sic], held at Ft. Ward, in Alexandria, Virginia. Images include Alice Hermann, Lani Herrmann, John Jackson, Chuck Perdue, Helen Schneyer, and Scott Dildine.
  - Festival of American Folklife, circa July 1-4, 1967, 16 slides: color; 35mm; AFC 2018/009: PH199-PH214 (Box 5)
    Photos from the first annual Festival of American Folklife, presented by the Smithsonian Institution, and held in Washington, D.C. Photos of various musicians and dancers.
  - Fox Hollow Festival, circa August 19-21, 1966, 54 slides: color; 35mm; AFC 2018/009: PH029-PH082 (Box 5)
    Photos from the first annual Fox Hollow Festival, hosted bob Bob and Evelyne Beers on their property in Petersburgh, New York. Images include shots of the campground, Children's Day, the craft area, the backstage area, Nan Perdue, Tossi Aaron, Sandy Paton, Caroline Paton, Cousin Thelma Bolton, The Young'uns, Scott Dildine, Penny Tricket, John Dildine, Bob Beers, Sarah Cleveland, the audience, the Paton family, Chuck Perdue, a jam session, The Boyer Girls, Marty Beers, Janet Boyers, the Beers family, Howie and Ann Mitchell, and Paul Cadwell and his wife.
  - Fox Hollow Festival, circa August 6-9, 1970, 15 slides: color; 35mm; AFC 2018/009: PH083-PH097 (Box 5)
    Images include shots of Michael Cooney, Utah Phillips, Joe Hickerson, John Whyn, sacred harp performance, The Carawans, The Armstrongs, and Bob Beers.
  - Fox Hollow Festival, August 1971, 1 slide: color; 35mm; AFC 2018/009: PH198 (Box 5)
    Image of Bill Spence, John Dildine, and Debbie.
  - Mariposa Folk Festival, circa July 24-26, 1970, 38 slides: color; 35mm; AFC 2018/009: PH098-PH135 (Box 5)
    The 1970 festival was held on Toronto Islands, Ontario, Canada. Images include shots of the ferry and also backstage, The Perth County Conspiracy, dancers, the Folklore Center booth, the old-time banjo workshop, the ballad workshop, Barry O'Neil, Billy Vanaver and Godulka, Norman Kennedy, Rosalie Sorrells, Artie Rose, Alanis Obomsiwen, and the Olympia Street Band (New Orleans).
  - Mariposa Folk Festival, circa July 9-11, 1971, 4 slides: color; 35mm; AFC 2018/009: PH136-PH139 (Box 5)
    The 1971 festival was held on Toronto Islands, Ontario, Canada. Images include shots of Larry Hanks, Owen McBride, and Billy Vanaver.
  - Mariposa Folk Festival, circa July 14-16, 1972, 7 slides: color; 35mm; AFC 2018/009: PH140-PH146 (Box 5)
    The 1972 festival was held on Toronto Islands, Ontario, Canada. Images include shots of the ferry, performers on a double-decker bus, dolls, and puppets.
  - Newport Folk Festival, circa July 10-16, 1967, 51 slides: color; 35mm; AFC 2018/009: PH147-PH197 (Box 5)
    Photos from the Newport Folk Festival, held in Newport, Rhode Island. Images include shots of John Dildine, various crew, Hedy West, Pete Seeger, folk dancing, Bread and Puppet, the crowd (audience), Joan Baez, Judy Collins, Mimi Farina, Buffy Sainte-Marie,
  - Dildine puppets, circa 1969-1970, 12 slides: color; 35mm; AFC 2018/009: PH215-PH226 (Box 6)
    Photos of some of the puppets, and members of the Dildine family.
  - Christmas TV show, December 1973, 6 slides: color; 35mm; AFC 2018/009: PH227-PH232 (Box 6)
    Images of Dildine family members and others from a Christmas TV special.
  - Ginny Dildine, playing the guitar, September 1957, 1 slide: color; 35mm; AFC 2018/009: PH233 (Box 6)
    Photo of Ginny Dildine, taken at the Pinecrest Cabin "hoot."
  - Beers family, 1966; 1973, 13 slides: color; 35mm; AFC 2018/009: PH234-PH246 (Box 6)
    All but one photo are from 1973; most were taken in a recording studio.
  - John Dildine and Ginny Dildine, circa 1960, 1 photograph: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH247 (Box 7)
    Studio portrait.
  - Early Dildine family performance, 1967, 1 photograph: black and white; 5 in. x 7 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH248 (Box 7)
    Photo of the family members onstage, including Atwood S. Barwick (Ginny's brother), Debbie Dildine, Connie Dildine, and Ginny and John Dildine. Photo by Carleton F. Smith.
  - The Dildines and the Perdues in performance, circa 1960s, 1 photograph: black and white; 10 in. x 8 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH249 (Box 7)
    Photo of John and Ginny Dildine, and Chuck and Nan Perdue onstage performing a song. Photo by Charles H. Cunningham.
  - Dildine family portrait (1 of 4), circa 1970s, 1 photograph: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH250 (Box 7)
    Studio portrait of Ginny, John, Connie, De3bbie, and Scott, with musical instruments and puppets.
  - Dildine family portrait (2 of 4), circa 1970s, 1 photograph: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH251 (Box 7)
    See description for AFC 2018/009: PH250.
  - Dildine family portrait (3 of 4), circa 1970s, 1 photograph: black and white; 5 in. x 7 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH252 (Box 7)
  - Dildine family portrait (4 of 4), circa 1970s, 1 photograph: black and white; 7 in. x 5 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH253 (Box 7)
  - Scott Dildine with the leatherwing bat puppet, circa 1970s, 1 photograph: black and white; 7 in. x 5 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH254 (Box 7)
    In performance.
  - "Good old man" (1 of 3), circa 1970s, 1 photograph: black and white; 5 in. x 7 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH255 (Box 7)
    Two puppets; in performance.
  - "Good old man" (2 of 3), circa 1970s, 1 photograph: black and white; 5 in. x 7 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH256 (Box 7)
    See description for AFC 2018/009: PH255.
  - "Good old man" (3 of 3), circa 1970s, 1 photograph: black and white; 5 in. x 7 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH257 (Box 7)
  - "Springfield Mountain," circa 1970s, 1 photograph: color; 3 1/2 in. x 5 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH258 (Box 7)
    The Dildine family onstage with puppets, in performance at the Fox Hollow Festival.
  - "Whistle daughter, whistle," circa 1970s, 1 photograph: color; 3 1/2 in. x 5 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH259 (Box 7)
    See description for AFC 2018/009: PH259.
  - Bob and Evelyn Beers in performance, 1963, 1 photograph: black and white; 9 1/2 in. x 6 1/2 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH260 (Box 7)
    Photographed at the 26th annual National Folk Festival, in Covington, Kentucky.
  - Paul Cadwell in performance, 1963, 1 photograph: black and white; 9 1/2 in. x 6 1/2 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH261 (Box 7)
    See description for AFC 2018/009: PH260.
  - Guy Carawan, undated, 1 photograph: black and white; 10 in. x 8 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH262 (Box 7)
  - Paul Clayton (1 of 2), 1967 or before, 1 photograph: black and white; -- in. x -- in.; AFC 2018/009: PH263 (Box 7)
    Clayton playing a banjo made in Beech Mountain, North Carolina. The photo is in box-folder 1/2.
  - Paul Clayton (2 of 2), 1967 or before, 1 photograph: black and white; 10 in. x 8 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH264 (Box 7)
    Clayton playing a southern mountain dulcimer from Kentucky. Photo credit: Photo-Sound Assoc.
  - Michael Cooney, undated, 1 photograph: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH265 (Box 7)
    Cooney playing a banjo (partially out of shot), outdoors.
  - Elizabeth Cotten and Lani Herrmann, undated, 1 photograph: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH266 (Box 7)
    Cotton is playing a guitar as Hermann listens and watches.
  - Charlotte "Char" Daniels, circa 1960s, 1 photograph: black and white; 8 1/2 in. x 7 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH267 (Box 7)
    Daniels is playing a Gibson guitar.
  - Patt Webb and Charlotte "Char" Daniels, circa 1960s, 1 photograph: black and white; 8 in. x 10 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH268 (Box 7)
  - Bonnie Dobson, undated, 1 photograph: black and white; 10 in. x 8 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH269 (Box 7)
    Photo of Dobson playing guitar, in performance.
  - Sara Grey, undated, 1 photograph: black and white; 7 in. x 5 in.; AFC 2018/009: PH270 (Box 7)